Jess Stearn Papers
Jess Stearn Papers
1932-1976
Stearn, Jess.
15 linear ft.
Typescript drafts, galley proofs, and research related to Edgar Cayce, the occult, parapsychology, and psychical research
148688
Biographical History
Jess Stearn (1914-2002) was an American journalist and author known for his writings on the occult.
After attending Syracuse University, Stearn worked for the New York Daily News as a reporter for seventeen years and then as an associate editor at Newsweek magazine. During his time as a reporter, he became interested in Edgar Cayce, an uneducated clairvoyant who could diagnose physical ailments, prescribe cures, and discuss a subject's past and future lives. Stearn published two biographies of Cayce, Edgar Cayce: The Sleeping Prophet and A Prophet in his Own Country: The Story of the Young Edgar Cayce. Through his interest in Cayce, Stearn went on to publish more than thirty other books on occult subjects such as reincarnation and psychic phenomena and informative subjects such as homosexuality and drugs. Some notable publications are The Search for the Girl with the Blue Eyes (1968), The Search for a Soul: Taylor Caldwell's Psychic Lives (1973), The Door to the Future (1963), Yoga, Youth and Reincarnation (1965), The Seekers (1972), Adventures into the Psychic (1969), The Miracle Workers: America's Psychic Consultants (1972), and The Sixth Man (1962).
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Jess Stearn Papers consist of biographical material, books, correspondence, and financial material.
Biographical material consists of a one-page article announcing Stearn's new column.
The bulk of this collection relates to Stearn's Books. The books for which the collection contains a significant amount of material are Edgar Cayce: The Sleeping Prophet and The Search for the Girl with the Blue Eyes. There are multiple drafts and a substantial amount of research for each book. Also included in this series are reviews of his books.
Correspondence consist of communications with Stearn's literary agencies, individuals, and fan mail Stearn received. Prominent individuals are Marcia Moore Acker, Hugh Lynn Cayce, and Gladys Davis Turner. Moore was an American writer, astrologer, and yoga teacher who was brought to the nation's attention through Stearn's book Yoga, Youth and Reincarnation. Hugh Lynn Cayce is the son of Edgar Cayce. Turner was Edgar Cayce's secretary and took notes on Cayce's psychic readings of various individuals.
Financial material contains the cost of the publicity tour of The Door to the Future in 1963, real estate tax for 1965, receipt for the Thunderbird motor Lodge in Virginia Beach, VA 1966, and a New York Telephone statement of calls and telegrams for May 1968.
Arrangement of the Collection
Books, correspondece, and writings are arranged alphabetically by title or name. Financial material is arranged chronologically.
Related Material
For more Edgar Cayce material, see the
Juliet Brooke Ballard Papers
. The
Long John Nebel Papers
includes an interview with Cayce from 1968 and two interviews with Jess Stearn (his name is spelled "Stern" in the Nebel listing), 1966 and 1968.
Separated Material
Two books -- The Reporter and The Miracle Workers: America's Psychic Consultants -- have been separated from the collection and transferred to Rare Books for cataloging. Please refer to to locate these items.
Subject and Genre Headings
Literature -- American Fiction; Religion and philosophy; Caldwell, Taylor, 1900-1985.; Cayce, Edgar, 1877-1945.; Cayce, Hugh Lynn.; Stearn, Jess.; Moore, Marcia, 1928-1979?; Reilly, Harold J., 1894 or 1895-1987.; Turner, Gladys Davis, 1905-1986.; Association for Research and Enlightenment.; Coward, McCann & Geoghegan, Inc.; Doubleday & Company, Inc.; Authors, American.; Clairvoyance.; Occultism.; Parapsychology.; Psychical research.; Reincarnation.; Yoga.; Articles.; Books.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Drafts (documents); Galley proofs.; Illustrations (layout features); Manuscripts for publication.; Research notes.; Authors.; Journalists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Ken and Joanne MacIver material relating to Mr Stearn's novel "The Search for the Girl with the Blue Eyes" may only be used with the written permission of Kenneth MacIver. Any such written permission documents will be retained by SCRC.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Jess Stearn, 1968-1973.
Inventory
- Biographical material
  - Article, 1965 (Box 1)
- Books
  - Adventures into the Psychic
    - Draft, 1969; 8 folders (Box 1)
  - The Door to the Future
    - Book reviews, 1962-1964 (Oversize 3)
  - Dr. Thompson's New Way for You to Cure Your Aching Back
    - Draft, 1973; 5 folders (Box 1)
    - Foundry proof, 1973 (Box 2)
    - Final galley, 1973 (Box 2)
  - Edgar Cayce: The Sleeping Prophet
    - Book reviews, 1966-1967 (Box 2)
    - Book reviews, 1966-1967 (Oversize 3)
    - Draft A, incomplete, 1966; 7 folders (Box 2)
    - Draft B, 1966; 7 folders (Box 3)
    - Final galley, 1966 (Box 3)
    - Page proof, 1966 (Box 3)
    - Page proof, 1967 (Box 4)
    - Publicity material, 1967 (Box  4)
    - Research material
      - Association of Research and Enlightenment (Box 4)
      - Biographical (Box 4)
      - Cayce family writings (Box 4)
      - Correspondences (Box 4)
      - Index cards, remedies for medical complaints taken from Edgar Cayce's Famous Black Book (Box 4)
      - Notes, handwritten (Box 4)
      - Printed material (Box 4)
      - Printed material (Box 5)
      - Psychic readings (Box 5)
      - Reilly, Harold J. (Box 5)
      - Writings about Cayce's readings (Box 5)
  - The Grapevine
    - Book reviews, 1963-1964 (Oversize 3)
  - The Miracle Workers: America's Psychic Consultants
    - Draft, 1972; 7 folders (Box 5)
    - Foundry proof, 1972 (Box 6)
    - Final galley, 1972 (Box 6)
  - The Reporter
    - Draft, 1970; pp. 1-400; 8 folders (Box 6)
    - Draft, 1970; pp. 401-419 (Box 7)
    - Original galley proof, 1970 (Box 7)
    - Page proof, 1970; 2 folders (Box 7)
  - The Search for a Soul: Taylor Caldwell's Psychic Lives
    - Draft, 1973; pp. 1-200; 4 folders (Box 7)
    - Draft, 1973; pp. 201-322; 3 folders (Box 8)
    - Final galley, 1973 (Box 8)
    - Foundry proof, 1973 (Box 8)
  - The Search for the Girl with the Blue Eyes
    - Article by Stearn, 1968 (Oversize 3)
    - Book reviews, 1968 (Oversize 3)
    - Draft A, incomplete, 1968; 4 folders (Box 8)
    - Draft A-C, incomplete, 1968; 12 folders (Box 9)
    - Draft C-D, incomplete, 1968; 12 folders (Box 10)
    - Draft E, 1968; pp. 1-100; 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Draft E, 1968; pp.101-395; 6 folders (Box 11)
    - Final galley, 1968 (Box 11)
    - Foundry proof, 1968 (Box 11)
    - Foundry proof, 1968 (Box 12)
    - Research material
      - Census information (Box 12)
      - Correspondence (Box 12)
        - Lewis, Madge, 1963 (Box 12)
        - Stevenson, Ian, Dr., 1962-1965 (Box 12)
        - Miscellaneous, 1963-1966 (Box 12)
        - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 12)
      - Notes, handwritten (Box 12)
      - Psychic sessions, 1962 (Box 12)
      - Psychic session 1-2, 2 folders (Box 12)
      - Psychic session 3-6, 4 folders (Box 13)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 13)
  - The Seekers
    - Draft A, 1969; pp. 1-350; 7 folders (Box 13)
    - Draft A, 1969; pp. 351-507; 4 folders (Box 14)
    - Draft B, incomplete, 1969; 10 folders (Box 14)
    - Draft B, incomplete, 1969 (Box 15)
    - Final galley, 1969 (Box 15)
    - Foundry proof, 1968 (Box 15)
    - Foundry proof, 1969 (Box 15)
  - The Sixth Man
    - Book reviews, 1961 (Oversize 3)
    - Publicity tour (Box 16)
  - A Time for Astrology
    - Book patch, 1965 (Oversize 3)
    - Draft A, 1971; 10 folders (Box 16)
    - Draft B, 1971; pp. 1-50 (Box 16)
    - Draft B, 1971; pp. 51-481; 9 folders (Box 17)
    - Draft C, 1971; pp. 1-350; 7 folders (Box 17)
    - Draft C, 1971; pp. 351-460; 2 folders (Box 18)
    - Research material, 1971 (Box 18)
    - Appendix proof, 1965; 3 folders (Oversize 1)
    - Appendix proof, 1965; 2 folders (Oversize 2)
    - Appendix notes, 1971; 5 folders (Box 18)
  - Yoga, Youth and Reincarnation
    - Article by Stearn, 1968 (Oversize 3)
    - Book reviews, 1965 (Oversize 3)
    - Draft A, incomplete, 1965; 4 folders (Box 18)
    - Draft B, incomplete, 1965 (Box 18)
    - Draft B, incomplete, 1965; 5 folders (Box 19)
    - Draft C, 1965; pp. 1-350; 7 folders (Box 19)
    - Draft C, 1965; pp. 351-536; 4 folders (Box 20)
    - Illustrations, 1965 (Oversize 3)
    - Miscellaneous, extra drafts of chapters (Box 20)
- Correspondence
  - Acker, Marcia Moore (Box 20)
  - Cayce, Hugh Lynn, 1965-1967 (Box 20)
  - Fan mail, 1965-1968; 2 folders (Box 20)
  - Literary agencies
    - Canadian Speakers' and Writers' Service, 1966-1967 (Box 20)
    - Coward, McCann & Geoghegan, Inc., 1968; 1976 (Box 20)
    - Doubleday & Company Inc., 1966-1968 (Box 20)
    - Doubleday Canada Liminted, 1966-1967 (Box 20)
    - The Sterling Lord Agency, 1967 (Box 20)
  - Turner, Gladys Davis, 1966; 1971 (Box 20)
  - Miscellaneous, letters from unknown individuals, Department of Taxation and Finance for the Sate of New York, and letters about Stearn (Box 20)
- Financial material
  - Finances, 1963; 1966,; 1968 (Box 20)